[Music]
Reedman
reads the Giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser Reedman chapter
8 The audience was clearly ill at ease.
They applauded at the final Assignment the applause was peace meal no longer a
crescendo of united enthusiast I ASM There were murmurs of
confusion. Jonas moved his hands together, clapping, but it was an automatic,
meaningless gesture that he wasn't even aware of. His mind had shut out all of the
earlier emotions: the anticipation, excitement, pride, and even the happy kinship with his
friends. Now he felt only humiliation and terror. The Chief Elder waited until the
uneasy applause subsided and and she spoke again. "I know," she said in her vibrant,
gracious voice, "that you are all concern That you feel I have made a
mistake." She smiled. The community, relieved from its discomfort very
slightly by her benign statement, seemed to breathe more easily. It was very
silent. Jonas looked up. "I have caused you anxiety," she said said. "I apologize to my
community." Her voice flowed over the assembled crowd. "We accept your apology," they all
uttered together.
"Jonas," she said, looking down at him, "I apologize to you in particular. I caused you
anguish." "I accept your apology jonice replied shakily please Please come to the stage
now." Earlier that day, dressing in his own dwelling, he had practiced the kind of
jaunty self- assured walk that he hoped he could make to the stage when his turn
came. All of that was forgotten now. He simply willed himself to stand, to move
his feet that felt weighted and clumsy, to go forward, up the steps and across
the platform until he stood at her side.
Reassuringly she placed her arm across his tense shoulders.
"Jonas has not been assigned," she informed the crowd, and his heart
sank. Then she went on. "Jonas has been selected. He blinked. What did that mean? He felt a
collective, questioning stir from the audience. They, too, were
puzzled. In a firm, commanding voice she announced, "Jonas has been selected to be
our next Receiver of Memory." Then he heard the gasp a sudden intake of breath, drawn sharply in
astonishment, by each of the seated citizens. He saw their faces; the eyes widened in
awe. And still he did not understand. "Such a selection is very, very
rare," the Chief Elder told the audience.
"Our community has only one Receiver. It is he who trains his
successor. "We have had our current Receiver for a very long time," she went
on. Jonas followed her eyes and saw that she was looking at one of the
Elders. The Committee of Elders was sitting together in a group; and the
Chief Elders eyes were now on one who sat in the midst which seemed oddly
separate from them. It was a man Jonas had never noticed before, a be bearded man with pale
eyes. He was watching Jonas intently. "We failed in our last selection," the Chief Elder said
solemnly. "It was 10 years ago, when Jonas was just a toddler. I will not dwell on the
experience because it causes us all terrible discomfort." Jonas didn't know what she
was referring to, but he could sense the discomfort of the audience. They shifted
uneasily in their seats. "We have not been hasty this time," she continued. "We could
not afford another failure." "Sometimes," she went on, speaking
now in a lighter tone, relaxing the tension in the Auditorium, "we are not
entirely certain about the Assignments, even after the most painstaking
observations. Sometimes we worry that the one assigned might not develop, through
training, every attribute necessary Els are still children, after
all. What we observe as playfulness and patience— —the requirements to become
Nurturer— —could, with maturity, be revealed as simply foolishness and
indolence. So we continue to observe during training, and to modify behavior when
necessary. "But the receiver in training cannot be observed, cannot be
modified this is stated quite clearly in the rule He is to be alone, apart, while he is
prepared by the current Receiver for the job which is the most honored in our
community." Alone? Apart? Jonas listened with increasing
unease. "Therefore the selection must be sound. It must be a unanimous choice of
the Committee. They can have no doubts, however fleeting. If, during the process, an Elder
reports a dream of uncertainty, that dream has the power to set a candidate aside
instantly. "Jonas was identified as a possible Receiver many years ago. We have observed him
meticulously. There were no dreams of uncertainty. "He has shown all of the
qualities that a Receiver must have." With her hands still firmly on his
shoulder, the Chief Elder listed the qualities.
Intelligence. she said. "We are all aware that Jonas has been a top student
throughout his school days.
Integrity she said next. "Jonas has, like all of us, committed minor
transgressions." She smiled at him. "We expect that. We hoped, also, that he would
present himself promptly for chastisement, and he has always done so. Courage, she went on.
"Only one of us here today has ever undergone the rigorous training required of a
Receiver. He, of course, is the most important member of the Committee: the
current Receiver. It was he who reminded us, again and again, of the courage required.
"Jonas," she said, turning to him, but speaking in a voice that the entire community could
hear, "the training required of you involves pain. Physical pain you felt
fear flutter within him. "You have never experienced that. Yes, you have scraped
your knees and falls from your bicycle.
Yes, you have crushed your finger in a door last year." Jonas nodded, agreeing, as he
recalled the incident, and its accompanying misery. "But you will be faced, now," she
explained gently, "with pain of a magnitude that none of us here can
comprehend because it is beyond our experience. The Receiver himself was not
able to describe it, only to remind us that you would be faced with it, that you
would need immense courage. We cannot prepare you for that.
"But we feel certain that you are brave," she said to him. He did not feel brave at
all. Not now. "The fourth essential attribute," the Chief Elder said, "is
wisdom. Jonas has not yet acquired that.
The acquisition of wisdom will come through his training. "We are convinced that Jonas has
the ability to acquire wisdom. That is what we looked for.
"Finally, The Receiver must have one more quality, and it is one which I can only
name, but not describe. I do not understand it. You members of the
community will not understand it, either.
Perhaps Jonas will, because the current Receiver has told us that Jonas already
has this quality. He calls it the Capacity to See
Beyond." The Chief Elder looked at Jonas with a question in her eyes. The audience
watched him, too. They were silent. For a moment he froze, consumed with
despair. He didn't have it, the whatever she had said He didn't know what it was.
Now was the moment when he would have to confess, to say, "No, I don't. I can't throw
himself on their mercy, ask their forgiveness, to explain that he had been
wrongly chosen he was not the right one at all. But when he looked out across the
crowd, the sea of faces, the thing happened again. The thing
that had happened with the apple. They changed. He blinked, and it was
gone. His shoulder straightened slightly. Briefly he felt a tiny sliver of shess for the first
time. She was still watching him. They all were. "I think it's true," he told the Chief
Elder and the community. "I don't understand it yet. I don't know what it is. But sometimes I
see something. And maybe it's beyond." She took her arm from his shoulders.
"Jonas," she said, speaking not to him alone but to the entire community of which he
was a part, "you will be trained to be our next Receiver of
Memory. We thank you for your childhood." Then she turned and left the
stage, left him there alone, standing and facing the crowd, which began
spontaneously the collective murmur of his name.
"Jonas." It was a whisper at first: hushed, barely audible. "Jonas.
Jonas and louder, faster. "JONAS. JONAS.
JONAS." With the chant, Jonas knew, the community was accepting him and his new
role, giving him life, the way they had given it to the new child
Caleb. His heart swelled with gratitude and pride. But at the same time he was filled with fear.
He did not know what his selection meant.
He did not know what he was to become. Or what would become of him
[Music]